Helen A. C. Long and May Chadwick Collection of Hamilton Manufacturing Photographs 6688 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Helen A. C. Long and May Chadwick Collection of Hamilton Manufacturing Photographs
1859-1910
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Helen A. C. Long
May Chadwick
Hamilton Manufacturing Company (Lowell, Mass.)
American Textile History Museum
6688 P
1 folders
1 file folder
Albumen print, carte de visite photographs, gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs of Charles B. Amory and Oliver H. Moulton of the Hamilton Manufacturing Company, mainly of rivers and canals.
10062633
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 09, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 28, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Hamilton Manufacturing Company was a manufacturer of cotton textiles, founded in Lowell, Massachusetts, in 1824.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of Charles B. Amory, Treasurer of the Hamilton Manufacturing Company, and his friend Oliver H. Moulton, Superintendent of the Hamilton Manufacturing Company. Includes photographs of the Merrimack River, Pawtucket Falls, and the Merrimack Canal in Lowell, Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6688 G: Helen A. C. Long and May Chadwick Collection of Hamilton Manufacturing Graphics
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection, gift of Helen A. C. Long and May Chadwick
Canals -- Massachusetts -- Lowell; Centennial Exhibition.; Cotton manufacture; Industries; Insurance surveys; Mill agents; Mill superintendents; Rivers; Textile factories; Textile industry; Voyages and travels; Waterfalls -- Massachusetts -- Lowell; Lowell (Mass.); Merrimack Canal (Lowell, Mass.); Northern Canal (Lowell, Mass.); Pawtucket Falls (Lowell, Mass.); United States -- Merrimack River; United States -- Army -- Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 24th (1861-1866); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Portraits; Amory, Charles B., 1841-1919; Moulton, Oliver H.; Amoskeag Manufacturing Company; Hamilton Manufacturing Company (Lowell, Mass.); Merrimack Manufacturing Company; Pemberton Manufacturing Company; Pepperell Manufacturing Company; American Textile History Museum
10062633
- Photographs of the Merrimack River and Hamilton Manufacturing officers, 1859-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Merrimack River, just above the Pawtucket Falls, Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.2, Before 1898; black and white photograph; 24.5 x 17 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a view of the Merrimack River in Lowell, Mass., just above the Pawtucket Falls. Photograph possibly taken from the south side of the river, looking north (towards Tyngsboro). The falls would be off to the right, out of the picture. Trees are nearly bare so it appears that it was taken in late autumn or early spring.
  - The Pawtucket Falls, Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.3, Before 1898; black and white photograph; 24 x 17 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a view of the Pawtucket Falls on the Merrimack River in Lowell, Mass. Photograph probably taken from the vantage point of what is now the School Street bridge, looking north (towards Tyngsboro). A few houses along what is now Pawtucket Boulevard are visible in the right background. Water level is quite high. Trees are nearly bare so photo appears to have been taken in late autumn or early spring.
  - Merrimack River in the Belvidere section of Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.4, Before 1898; black and white photograph; 24 x 17 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the Merrimack River in the Belvidere section of Lowell, Mass., just below Stackpole Street and East Merrimack Street. Taken from the Belvidere side of the river; Stackpole and East Merrimack Sts. would be off to the left. The Centralville (Bridge Street) bridge is seen in the distance, and some of the mill chimneys beyond it. What is now the Hunts Falls Bridge has not yet been built. Trees are nearly bare so photo appears to have been taken in late autumn or early spring.
  - Northern Canal and Merrimack River, Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.5, Before 1898; black and white photograph; 24.25 x 17.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the Northern Canal (on the left) running parallel to the Merrimack River (on the right) in Lowell, Mass. An ironwork bridge (what is now the School Street Bridge) is barely visible in the left background. Viewpoint is looking north; the Pawtucket Falls would be beyond the bridge on the left. Handwriting on reverse of photo indicates Pawtucket Canal, which is incorrect. Houses on the right would be in Pawtucketville, clustered around the Mammoth Road area. The bell tower in the center background is probably the Pawtucket Congregational Church; this building was replaced with a red brick Romanesque building in 1898.
  - Charles B. Amory, Captain, Co. I, 24th Reg. Massachusetts Volunteers, ATHM# 1993.28.6, 1863-07; black and white photograph; 5.5 x 7.5 cm. (w/out mount); 11.5 x 15.25 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Albumen print. Image depicts Amory in his military uniform. Seen from the chest up. Written on reverse: "Chas. B. Amory, Captain co. I 24th Regt. Mass. Vol. July 1863." Amory was a the treasurer of the Hamilton Mfg. Co. in Lowell, Mass., from approximately 1885 until 1909, and a director of the company until his death in 1919. He was a close friend of Oliver H. Moulton, superintendent of the Hamilton Mfg. Co. in Lowell, Mass. See 1993.28.7 for a much later photo of Amory.
  - Charles B. Amory, Boston, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.7, 1910; black and white photograph; 9.75 x 14 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Charles B. Amory, Boston, Mass. Gelatin silver print, [ca1910]. Image depicts Amory seated in a chair, wearing a three-piece suit and a tie. He has a white mustache and sideburns, but a cleanshaven chin. Amory was a the treasurer of the Hamilton Mfg. Co. in Lowell, Mass., from approximately 1885 until 1909, and a director of the company until his death in 1919. He was a close friend of Oliver H. Moulton, superintendent of the Hamilton Mfg. Co. in Lowell, Mass. See 1993.28.6 for an 1863 photo of Amory.
  - Oliver H. Moulton, ATHM# 1993.28.8, 1859-1864; black and white photograph; 5.75 x 8.75 cm.(w/out mount); 6.25 x 10.25 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Eaton & Bachelder's Photographic Gallery, Manchester, N.H. Albumen print carte de visite. Image depicts Moulton, an overseer in the Amoskeag Mfg. Company, Manchester, N.H., during this period, standing in a studio setting, with his right arm leaning on a counter; a patterned drape is tied behind him. He wears a frock coat, vest, and tie, and has a beard very reminiscent of Abraham Lincoln's. Moulton is listed in the 1860 Manchester, N.H., directory as superintendent of Amoskeag; by 1865 he is the superintendent of the Hamilton Mfg. Company in Lowell, Mass. See 1993.28.9 for a much later photo of Moulton.
  - Oliver Howe Moulton, in his office at the Hamilton Manufacturing Co., Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.9, 1900-1905; black and white photograph; 5 x 3.75 cm. (w/out mount); 8.5 x 7.25 cm. (w/mount) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts Moulton, superintendent of the Hamilton Manufacturing Co. from 1865 to 1905, sitting behind his desk in his office. He wears a three-piece suit and a tie; he has white hair, a beard and a mustache. His desk is piled with books, a lamp, and rolled drawings.
  - Merrimack Canal, Lowell, MA, ATHM# 1993.28.10, 1900; black and white photograph; 10.25 x 7.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the Merrimack Canal in Lowell, Mass., looking towards the Merrimack Mfg. Co. (mill building with tower in the distance). The Dutton Street boardinghouses are barely visible through the trees on the left. Trees are nearly bare so photo appears to have been taken in late autumn or early spring.
  - Unidentified view of mills on river, ATHM# 1993.28.11, Before 1900; black and white photograph; 7.75 x 6.5 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print. Image depicts mill buildings on an unidentified river; possibly Lowell, MA but not Merrimack River
  - United States International Exhibition, Philadelphia, Penn., admission ticket, with photo attached, ATHM# 1993.28.12, 1876; black and white photograph; 4.5 x 6 cm. (w/out mount); 7.25 x 11 cm. (w/mount, folded) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Gelatin silver print (attached). Ticket issued to Oliver H. Moulton as an exhibitor at the United States International Exhibition in Philadelphia, Penn., usuable between May 10 and Nov. 10 of 1876. Photo of Moulton attached, showing him from the shoulders up. Moulton was superintendent of the Hamilton Mfg. Company in Lowell, Mass., at this time.